<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="new-in-2">
  <title>What's new in Spring 2.0 and 2.5?</title>

  <section id="new-in-2-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>If you have been using the Spring Framework for some time, you will
    be aware that Spring has undergone two major revisions: Spring 2.0,
    released in October 2006, and Spring 2.5, released in November 2007.</para>

    <sidebar id="new-in-2-intro-java">
      <title>Java SE and Java EE Support</title>

      <para>The Spring Framework continues to be compatible with all versions
      of Java since (and including) Java 1.4.2. This means that Java 1.4.2,
      Java 5 and Java 6 are supported, although some advanced functionality of
      the Spring Framework will not be available to you if you are committed to
      using Java 1.4.2. Spring 2.5 introduces dedicated support for Java 6,
      after Spring 2.0's in-depth support for Java 5 throughout the
      framework.</para>

      <para>Furthermore, Spring remains compatible with J2EE 1.3 and higher,
      while at the same time introducing dedicated support for Java EE 5. This
      means that Spring can be consistently used on application servers such
      as BEA WebLogic 8.1, 9.0, 9.2 and 10, IBM WebSphere 5.1, 6.0, 6.1 and 7,
      Oracle OC4J 10.1.3 and 11, JBoss 3.2, 4.0, 4.2 and 5.0, as well as Tomcat
      4.1, 5.0, 5.5 and 6.0, Jetty 4.2, 5.1 and 6.1, Resin 2.1, 3.0 and 3.1
      and GlassFish V1 and V2.</para>

			<para><emphasis>NOTE: We generally recommend using the most recent
			version of each application server generation. In particular,
			make sure you are using BEA WebLogic 8.1 SP6 or higher and
			WebSphere 6.0.2.19 / 6.1.0.9 or higher, respectively, when using
			those WebLogic and WebSphere generations with Spring 2.5.</emphasis></para>
    </sidebar>

    <para>This chapter is a guide to the new and improved features of Spring
    2.0 and 2.5. It is intended to provide a high-level summary so that
    seasoned Spring architects and developers can become immediately familiar
    with the new Spring 2.x functionality. For more in-depth information on
    the features, please refer to the corresponding sections hyperlinked from
    within this chapter.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="new-in-2-ioc">
    <title>The Inversion of Control (IoC) container</title>

    <para>One of the areas that contains a considerable number of 2.0
    and 2.5 improvements is Spring's IoC container.</para>

    <section id="new-in-2-ioc-scopes">
      <title>New bean scopes</title>

      <para>Previous versions of Spring had IoC container level support for
      exactly two distinct bean scopes (singleton and prototype). Spring 2.0
      improves on this by not only providing a number of additional scopes
      depending on the environment in which Spring is being deployed (for
      example, request and session scoped beans in a web environment), but
      also by providing integration points so that Spring users can create
      their own scopes.</para>

      <para>It should be noted that although the underlying (and internal)
      implementation for singleton- and prototype-scoped beans has been
      changed, this change is totally transparent to the end user... no
      existing configuration needs to change, and no existing configuration
      will break.</para>

      <para>Both the new and the original scopes are detailed in
      <xref linkend="beans-factory-scopes"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-ioc-configuration">
      <title>Easier XML configuration</title>

      <para>Spring XML configuration is now even easier, thanks to the advent
      of the new XML configuration syntax based on XML Schema. If you want to
      take advantage of the new tags that Spring provides (and the Spring team
      certainly suggest that you do because they make configuration less
      verbose and easier to read), then do read <xref linkend="xsd-config"/>.</para>

      <para>On a related note, there is a new, updated DTD for Spring 2.0 that
      you may wish to reference if you cannot take advantage of the XML
      Schema-based configuration. The DOCTYPE declaration is included below
      for your convenience, but the interested reader should definitely read
      the <filename>'spring-beans-2.0.dtd'</filename> DTD included in the
      <filename class="directory">'dist/resources'</filename> directory of the
      Spring 2.5 distribution.</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;!DOCTYPE beans PUBLIC "-//SPRING//DTD BEAN 2.0//EN"
		  "http://www.springframework.org/dtd/spring-beans-2.0.dtd"&gt;</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-ioc-custom-configuration">
      <title>Extensible XML authoring</title>

      <para>Not only is XML configuration easier to write, it is now also
      extensible.</para>

      <para>What 'extensible' means in this context is that you, as an
      application developer, or (more likely) as a third party framework or
      product vendor, can write custom tags that other developers can then
      plug into their own Spring configuration files. This allows you to have
      your own domain specific language (the term is used loosely here) of
      sorts be reflected in the specific configuration of your own
      components.</para>

      <para>Implementing custom Spring tags may not be of interest to every
      single application developer or enterprise architect using Spring in
      their own projects. We expect third-party vendors to be highly
      interested in developing custom configuration tags for use in Spring
      configuration files.</para>

      <para>The extensible configuration mechanism is documented in <xref
      linkend="extensible-xml"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-ioc-annotations">
      <title>Annotation-driven configuration</title>

      <para>Spring 2.0 introduced support for various annotations for
      configuration purposes, such as <interfacename>@Transactional</interfacename>,
      <interfacename>@Required</interfacename> and <interfacename>@PersistenceContext</interfacename>
      /<interfacename>@PersistenceUnit</interfacename>.</para>

      <para>Spring 2.5 introduces support for a complete set of configuration
      annotations: <interfacename>@Autowired</interfacename> in combination
      with support for the JSR-250 annotations <interfacename>@Resource</interfacename>,
      <interfacename>@PostConstruct</interfacename> and <interfacename>@PreDestroy</interfacename>
      .</para>

      <para>Annotation-driven bean configuration is discussed in <xref
      linkend="beans-annotation-config"/>. Check out annotation support
      for Spring MVC as well: <xref linkend="new-in-2-web-annotations"/></para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-ioc-component-scanning">
      <title>Autodetecting components in the classpath</title>

      <para>Spring 2.5 introduces support component scanning: autodetecting
      annotated components in the classpath. Typically, such component classes
      will be annotated with stereotypes such as <interfacename>@Component</interfacename>,
      <interfacename>@Repository</interfacename>, <interfacename>@Service</interfacename>,
      <interfacename>@Controller</interfacename>. Depending on the application
      context configuration, such component classes will be autodetected and
      turned into Spring bean definitions, not requiring explicit configuration
      for each such bean.</para>

      <para>Annotation-driven bean configuration is discussed in <xref
      linkend="beans-stereotype-annotations"/>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="new-in-2-aop">
    <title>Aspect Oriented Programming (AOP)</title>

    <para>Spring 2.0 has a much improved AOP offering. The Spring AOP
    framework itself is markedly easier to configure in XML, and significantly
    less verbose as a result; and Spring 2.0 integrates with the AspectJ
    pointcut language and @AspectJ aspect declaration style. The chapter
    entitled <xref linkend="aop"/> is dedicated to describing this new
    support.</para>

    <section id="new-in-2-aop-configuration">
      <title>Easier AOP XML configuration</title>

      <para>Spring 2.0 introduces new schema support for defining aspects
      backed by regular Java objects. This support takes advantage of the
      AspectJ pointcut language and offers fully typed advice (i.e. no more
      casting and <literal>Object[]</literal> argument manipulation). Details
      of this support can be found in <xref linkend="aop-schema"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-aop-aspectj">
      <title>Support for @AspectJ aspects</title>

      <para>Spring 2.0 also supports aspects defined using the @AspectJ
      annotations. These aspects can be shared between AspectJ and Spring AOP,
      and require (honestly!) only some simple configuration. Said support for
      @AspectJ aspects is discussed in <xref
      linkend="aop-ataspectj"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-aop-bean-pointcuts">
      <title>Support for bean name pointcut element</title>

      <para>Spring 2.5 introduces support for the <literal>bean(...)</literal>
      pointcut element, matching specific named beans according to Spring-defined
      bean names. See <xref linkend="aop-pointcuts-designators"/> for details.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-aop-load-time-weaving">
      <title>Support for AspectJ load-time weaving</title>

      <para>Spring 2.5 introduces explicit support AspectJ load-time weaving,
      as alternative to the proxy-based AOP framework. The new
      <literal>context:load-time-weaver</literal> configuration element
      automatically activates AspectJ aspects as defined in AspectJ's
      <literal>META-INF/aop.xml</literal> descriptor, applying them to the
      current application context through registering a transformer with the
      underlying ClassLoader. Note that this only works in environments with
      class transformation support. Check out <xref linkend="aop-aj-ltw"/>
      for the capabilities and limitations.</para>
     </section>
  </section>

  <section id="new-in-2-middle-tier">
    <title>The Middle Tier</title>

    <section id="new-in-2-middle-tier-transaction-configuration">
      <title>Easier configuration of declarative transactions in XML</title>

      <para>The way that transactions are configured in Spring 2.0 has been
      changed significantly. The previous 1.2.x style of configuration
      continues to be valid (and supported), but the new style is markedly
      less verbose and is the recommended style. Spring 2.0 also ships with an
      AspectJ aspects library that you can use to make pretty much any object
      transactional - even objects not created by the Spring IoC container.</para>

      <para>Spring 2.5 supports convenient annotation-driven transaction
      management in combination with load-time weaving, through the use of
      <literal>context:load-time-weaver</literal> in combination with
      <literal>tx:annotation-driven mode="aspectj"</literal>.</para>

      <para>The chapter entitled <xref linkend="transaction"/> contains all
      of the details.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-middle-tier-websphere">
      <title>Full WebSphere transaction management support</title>

      <para>Spring 2.5 explicitly supports IBM's WebSphere Application Server,
      in particular with respect to WebSphere's transaction manager.
      Transaction suspension is now fully supported through the use of
      WebSphere's new <interfacename>UOWManager</interfacename> API, which
      is available on WAS 6.0.2.19+ and 6.0.1.9+.</para>

      <para>So if you run a Spring-based application on the WebSphere
      Application Server, we highly recommend to use Spring 2.5's
      <classname>WebSphereUowTransactionManager</classname> as your
      <interfacename>PlatformTransactionManager</interfacename> of choice.
      This is also IBM's official recommendation.</para>

      <para>For automatic detection of the underlying JTA-based transaction
      platform, consider the use of Spring 2.5's new
      <literal>tx:jta-transaction-manager</literal> configuration element.
      This will autodetect BEA WebLogic and IBM WebSphere, registering the
      appropriate <interfacename>PlatformTransactionManager</interfacename>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-middle-tier-jpa">
      <title>JPA</title>

      <para>Spring 2.0 ships with a JPA abstraction layer that is similar in
      intent to Spring's JDBC abstraction layer in terms of scope and general
      usage patterns.</para>

      <para>If you are interested in using a JPA-implementation as the
      backbone of your persistence layer, <xref linkend="orm-jpa"/> is
      dedicated to detailing Spring's support and value-add in this area.</para>

      <para>Spring 2.5 upgrades its OpenJPA support to OpenJPA 1.0,
      with support for advanced features such as savepoints.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-middle-tier-async-jms">
      <title>Asynchronous JMS</title>

      <para>Prior to Spring 2.0, Spring's JMS offering was limited to sending
      messages and the <emphasis>synchronous</emphasis> receiving of messages.
      This functionality (encapsulated in the
      <classname>JmsTemplate</classname> class) is great, but it doesn't
      address the requirement for the <emphasis>asynchronous</emphasis>
      receiving of messages.</para>

      <para>Spring 2.0 now ships with full support for the reception of
      messages in an asynchronous fashion, as detailed in
      <xref linkend="jms-asynchronousMessageReception"/>.</para>

      <para>As of Spring 2.5, the JCA style of setting up asynchronous
      message listeners is supported as well, through the
      <classname>GenericMessageEndpointManager</classname> facility.
      This is an alternative to the standard JMS listener facility, allowing
      closer integration with message brokers such as ActiveMQ and JORAM.
      See <xref linkend="jms-jca-message-endpoint-manager"/>.</para>

      <para>Spring 2.5 also introduces an XML namespace for simplifying JMS
      configuration, offering concise configuration of a large numbers of
      listeners. This namespace supports both the standard JMS listener facility
      as well as the JCA setup style, with minimal changes in the configuration.
      See <xref linkend="jms-namespace"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-middle-tier-jdbc">
      <title>JDBC</title>

      <para>There are some small (but nevertheless notable) new classes in the
      Spring Framework's JDBC support library. The first, <link
      linkend="jdbc-NamedParameterJdbcTemplate"><classname>NamedParameterJdbcTemplate</classname></link>,
      provides support for programming JDBC statements using named parameters
      (as opposed to programming JDBC statements using only classic
      placeholder (<literal>'?'</literal>) arguments.</para>

      <para>Another of the new classes, the <link
      linkend="jdbc-SimpleJdbcTemplate"><classname>SimpleJdbcTemplate</classname></link>,
      is aimed at making using the <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> even
      easier to use when you are developing against Java 5+ (Tiger).</para>

      <para>Spring 2.5 significantly extends the functionality of
      <classname>SimpleJdbcTemplate</classname> and introduces
      <classname>SimpleJdbcCall</classname> and <classname>SimpleJdbcInsert</classname>
      operation objects.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="new-in-2-web">
    <title>The Web Tier</title>

    <para>The web tier support has been <emphasis>substantially</emphasis>
    improved and expanded in Spring 2.0, with annotation-based controllers
    introduced in Spring 2.5.</para>

    <section id="new-in-2-web-convention">
      <title>Sensible defaulting in Spring MVC</title>

      <para>For a lot of projects, sticking to established conventions and
      having reasonable defaults is just what the projects need... this theme
      of convention-over-configuration now has explicit support in Spring MVC.
      What this means is that if you establish a set of naming conventions for
      your <literal>Controllers</literal> and views, you can
      <emphasis>substantially</emphasis> cut down on the amount of XML
      configuration that is required to setup handler mappings, view
      resolvers, <classname>ModelAndView</classname> instances, etc. This is a
      great boon with regards to rapid prototyping, and can also lend a degree
      of (always good-to-have) consistency across a codebase.</para>

      <para>Spring MVC's convention-over-configuration support is detailed in
      <xref linkend="mvc-coc"/></para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-web-portlet">
      <title>Portlet framework</title>

      <para>Spring 2.0 ships with a Portlet framework that is conceptually
      similar to the Spring MVC framework. Detailed coverage of the Spring
      Portlet framework can be found in <xref linkend="portlet"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-web-annotations">
      <title>Annotation-based controllers</title>

      <para>Spring 2.5 introduces an annotation-based programming model for MVC
      controllers, using annotations such as <interfacename>@RequestMapping</interfacename>,
      <interfacename>@RequestParam</interfacename>, <interfacename>@ModelAttribute</interfacename>,
      etc. This annotation support is available for both Servlet MVC and Portlet
      MVC. Controllers implemented in this style do not have to extend specific 
      base classes or implement specific interfaces. Furthermore, they do not 
      usually have direct dependencies on Servlet or Portlet API's, although 
      they can easily get access to Servlet or Portlet facilities if desired.
      For further details, see <xref linkend="mvc-annotation"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-web-form-tags">
      <title>A form tag library for Spring MVC</title>

      <para>A rich JSP tag library for Spring MVC was <emphasis>the</emphasis>
      JIRA issue that garnered the most votes from Spring users (by a wide
      margin).</para>

      <para>Spring 2.0 ships with a full featured JSP tag library that makes
      the job of authoring JSP pages much easier when using Spring MVC; the
      Spring team is confident it will satisfy all of those developers who
      voted for the issue on JIRA. The new tag library is itself covered in
      <xref linkend="view-jsp-formtaglib"/>, and a quick
      reference to all of the new tags can be found in the appendix entitled
      <xref linkend="spring-form.tld"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-web-tiles2">
      <title>Tiles 2 support</title>

      <para>Spring 2.5 ships support for Tiles 2, the next generation of the
      popular Tiles templating framework. This supersedes Spring's former support
      for Tiles 1, as included in Struts 1.x. See <xref linkend="view-tiles"/>
      for details.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-web-jsf12">
      <title>JSF 1.2 support</title>

      <para>Spring 2.5 supports JSF 1.2, providing a JSF 1.2 variant of Spring's
      <classname>DelegatingVariableResolver</classname> in the form of the new
      <classname>SpringBeanFacesELResolver</classname>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-web-jaxws">
      <title>JAX-WS support</title>

      <para>Spring 2.5 fully supports JAX-WS 2.0/2.1, as included in Java 6 and Java EE 5.
      JAX-WS is the successor of JAX-RPC, allowing access to WSDL/SOAP-based web
      services as well as JAX-WS style exposure of web services.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="new-in-2-other">
    <title>Everything else</title>

    <para>This final section outlines all of the other new and improved Spring
    2.0/2.5 features and functionality.</para>

    <section id="new-in-2-other-dynamic-language-support">
      <title>Dynamic language support</title>

      <para>Spring 2.0 introduced support for beans written in languages other
      than Java, with the currently supported dynamic languages being JRuby,
      Groovy and BeanShell. This dynamic language support is comprehensively
      detailed in <xref linkend="dynamic-language"/>.</para>

      <para>Spring 2.5 refines the dynamic languages support with autowiring
      and support for the recently released JRuby 1.0.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-other-testing">
      <title>Enhanced testing support</title>

      <para>Spring 2.5 introduces the <emphasis>Spring TestContext
      Framework</emphasis> which provides annotation-driven unit and integration
      testing support that is agnostic of the actual testing framework in use.
      The same techniques and annotation-based configuration used in, for
      example, a JUnit 3.8 environment can also be applied to tests written with
      JUnit 4.4, TestNG, etc.</para>

      <para>In addition to providing generic and extensible testing
      infrastructure, the <emphasis>Spring TestContext Framework</emphasis>
      provides out-of-the-box support for Spring-specific integration testing
      functionality such as <link linkend="testcontext-ctx-management">context
      management and caching</link>, <link
      linkend="testcontext-fixture-di">dependency injection of test
      fixtures</link>, and <link linkend="testcontext-tx">transactional test
      management</link> with default rollback semantics.</para>

      <para>To discover how this new testing support can assist you with writing
      unit and integration tests, consult <xref linkend="testcontext-framework"/>
      of the revised testing chapter.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-other-jmx">
      <title>JMX support</title>

      <para>The Spring Framework 2.0 has support for
      <literal>Notifications</literal>; it is also possible to exercise
      declarative control over the registration behavior of MBeans with an
      <literal>MBeanServer</literal>.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <xref linkend="jmx-notifications"/>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <xref linkend="jmx-exporting-registration-behavior"/>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Furthermore, Spring 2.5 provides a
      <link linkend="jmx-context-mbeanexport"><literal>context:mbean-export</literal></link>
      configuration element for convenient registration of annotated bean classes,
      detecting Spring's <interfacename>@ManagedResource</interfacename> annotation.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-other-jca">
      <title>Deploying a Spring application context as JCA adapter</title>

      <para>Spring 2.5 supports the deployment of a Spring application context
      as JCA resource adapter, packaged as a JCA RAR file. This allows headless
      application modules to be deployed into J2EE servers, getting access to
      all the server's infrastructure e.g. for executing scheduled tasks,
      listening for incoming messages, etc.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-other-taskexecutor">
      <title>Task scheduling</title>

      <para>Spring 2.0 offers an abstraction around the scheduling of tasks.
      For the interested developer, <xref linkend="scheduling-task-executor"/>
      contains all of the details.</para>

      <para>The <interfacename>TaskExecutor</interfacename> abstraction is used
      throughout the framework itself as well, e.g. for the asynchronous JMS support.
      In Spring 2.5, it is also used in the JCA environment support.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="new-in-2-other-java5">
      <title>Java 5 (Tiger) support</title>

      <para>Find below pointers to documentation describing some of the new
      Java 5 support in Spring 2.0 and 2.5.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <xref linkend="beans-annotation-config"/>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <xref linkend="beans-required-annotation"/>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <xref linkend="transaction-declarative-annotations"/>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <xref linkend="jdbc-SimpleJdbcTemplate"/>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <xref linkend="orm-jpa"/>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <xref linkend="aop-ataspectj"/>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <xref linkend="aop-atconfigurable"/>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="new-in-2-migrating">
    <title>Migrating to Spring 2.5</title>

    <para>This final section details issues that may arise during any
    migration from Spring 1.2/2.0 to Spring 2.5.</para>

    <para>Upgrading to Spring 2.5 from a Spring 2.0.x application should
    simply be a matter of dropping the Spring 2.5 jar into the appropriate
    location in your application's directory structure. We highly recommend
    upgrading to Spring 2.5 from any Spring 2.0 application that runs on
    JDK 1.4.2 or higher, in particular when running on Java 5 or higher,
    leveraging the significant configuration conveniences and performance
    improvements that Spring 2.5 has to offer.</para>

    <para>Whether an upgrade from Spring 1.2.x will be as seamless depends on
    how much of the Spring APIs you are using in your code. Spring 2.0
    removed pretty much all of the classes and methods previously marked
    as deprecated in the Spring 1.2.x codebase, so if you have been using
    such classes and methods, you will of course have to use alternative
    classes and methods (some of which are summarized below).</para>

    <para>With regards to configuration, Spring 1.2.x style XML configuration
    is 100%, satisfaction-guaranteed compatible with the Spring 2.5 library.
    Of course if you are still using the Spring 1.2.x DTD, then you won't be
    able to take advantage of some of the new Spring 2.0 functionality (such
    as <link linkend="new-in-2-ioc-scopes">scopes</link> and <link
    linkend="new-in-2-aop-configuration">easier AOP</link> and <link
    linkend="new-in-2-middle-tier-transaction-configuration">transaction
    configuration</link>), but nothing will blow up.</para>

    <para>The suggested migration strategy is to drop in the Spring 2.5 jar(s)
    to benefit from the improved code present in the release (bug fixes,
    optimizations, etc.). You can then, on an incremental basis, choose to
    start using the new Spring 2.5 features and configuration. For example,
    you could choose to start configuring just your aspects in the new Spring
    2 style; it is perfectly valid to have 90% of your configuration using
    the old-school Spring 1.2.x configuration (which references the 1.2.x
    DTD), and have the other 10% using the new Spring 2 configuration (which
    references the 2.0/2.5 DTD or XSD). Bear in mind that you are not forced to
    upgrade your XML configuration should you choose to drop in the Spring 2.5
    libraries.</para>

    <section id="new-in-2-migrating-changes">
      <title>Changes</title>

      <para>For a comprehensive list of changes, consult the
      <filename>'changelog.txt'</filename> file that is located in the top
      level directory of the Spring Framework distribution.</para>

      <section id="new-in-2-migrating-jdk">
        <title>Supported JDK versions</title>

        <para>As of Spring 2.5, support for JDK 1.3 has been removed,
        following Sun's official deprecation of JDK 1.3 in late 2006.
        If you haven't done so already, upgrade to JDK 1.4.2 or higher.</para>

        <para>If you need to stick with an application server that only supports
        JDK 1.3, such as WebSphere 4.0 or 5.0, we recommend using the
        Spring Framework version 2.0.7/2.0.8 which still supports JDK 1.3.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="new-in-2-migrating-packaging">
        <title>Jar packaging in Spring 2.5</title>

        <para>As of Spring 2.5, Spring Web MVC is no longer part of the
        <filename class="libraryfile">'spring.jar'</filename> file. Spring MVC
        can be found in <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-webmvc.jar'</filename>
        and <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-webmvc-portlet.jar'</filename>
        in the <literal>lib/modules</literal> directory of the distribution.
        Furthermore, the Struts 1.x support has been factored out into
        <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-webmvc-struts.jar'</filename>.</para>

        <para><emphasis>Note: The commonly used Spring's <classname>DispatcherServlet</classname>
        is part of Spring's Web MVC framework.</emphasis> As a consequence,
        you need to add <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-webmvc.jar'</filename>
        (or <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-webmvc-portlet/struts.jar'</filename>)
        to a <filename class="libraryfile">'spring.jar'</filename> scenario,
        even if you are just using <classname>DispatcherServlet</classname>
        for remoting purposes (e.g. exporting Hessian or HTTP invoker services).</para>

        <para>Spring 2.0's <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-jmx.jar'</filename>
        and <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-remoting.jar'</filename> have been
        merged into Spring 2.5's <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-context.jar'</filename>
        (for the JMX and non-HTTP remoting support) and partly into
        <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-web.jar'</filename>
        (for the HTTP remoting support).</para>

        <para>Spring 2.0's <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-support.jar'</filename>
        has been renamed to <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-context-support.jar'</filename>,
        expressing the actual support relationship more closely.
        <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-portlet.jar'</filename> has been
        renamed to <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-webmvc-portlet.jar'</filename>,
        since it is technically a submodule of Spring's Web MVC framework.
        Analogously, <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-struts.jar'</filename>
        has been renamed to <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-webmvc-struts.jar'</filename>.
        </para>

        <para>Spring 2.0's <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-jdo.jar'</filename>,
        <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-jpa.jar'</filename>,
        <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-hibernate3.jar'</filename>,
        <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-toplink.jar'</filename>
        and <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-ibatis.jar'</filename>
        have been combined into Spring 2.5's coarse-granular
        <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-orm.jar'</filename>.</para>

        <para>Spring 2.5's <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-test.jar'</filename>
        supersedes the previous <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-mock.jar'</filename>,
        indicating the stronger focus on the test context framework.
        Note that <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-test.jar'</filename>
        contains everything <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-mock.jar'</filename>
        contained in previous Spring versions; hence it can be used as a
        straightforward replacement for unit and integration testing purposes.</para>

        <para>Spring 2.5's <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-tx.jar'</filename>
        supersedes the previous <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-dao.jar'</filename>
        and <filename class="libraryfile">'spring-jca.jar'</filename> files,
        indicating the stronger focus on the transaction framework.</para>

        <para>Spring 2.5 ships its framework jars as OSGi-compliant bundles
        out of the box. This facilitates use of Spring in OSGi environments,
        not requiring custom packaging anymore.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="new-in-2-migrating-xml-configuration">
        <title>XML configuration</title>

        <para>Spring 2.0 ships with XSDs that describe Spring's XML metadata
        format in a much richer fashion than the DTD that shipped with
        previous versions. The old DTD is still fully supported, but if
        possible you are encouraged to reference the XSD files at the top of
        your bean definition files.</para>

        <para>One thing that has changed in a (somewhat) breaking fashion is
        the way that bean scopes are defined. If you are using the Spring 1.2
        DTD you can continue to use the <literal>'singleton'</literal>
        attribute. You can however choose to <link
        linkend="new-in-2-ioc-configuration">reference the new Spring 2.0
        DTD</link> which does not permit the use of the
        <literal>'singleton'</literal> attribute, but rather uses the
        <literal>'scope'</literal> attribute to define the bean lifecycle
        scope.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="new-in-2-migrating-deprecated">
        <title>Deprecated classes and methods</title>

        <para>A number of classes and methods that previously were marked as
        <literal>@deprecated</literal> have been removed from the Spring 2.0
        codebase. The Spring team decided that the 2.0 release marked a fresh
        start of sorts, and that any deprecated 'cruft' was better excised now
        instead of continuing to haunt the codebase for the foreseeable
        future.</para>

        <para>As mentioned previously, for a comprehensive list of changes,
        consult the <filename>'changelog.txt'</filename> file that is located
        in the top level directory of the Spring Framework distribution.</para>

        <para>The following classes/interfaces have been removed as of Spring
        2.0:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><interfacename>ResultReader</interfacename> : Use the
            <interfacename>RowMapper</interfacename> interface instead.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><classname>BeanFactoryBootstrap</classname> : Consider using
            a <interfacename>BeanFactoryLocator</interfacename> or a custom
            bootstrap class instead.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section id="new-in-2-migrating-ojb">
        <title>Apache OJB</title>

        <para>As of Spring 2.0, support for Apache OJB was <emphasis>totally
        removed</emphasis> from the main Spring source tree. The Apache OJB
        integration library is still available, but can be found in its new
        home in the <ulink url="https://springmodules.dev.java.net/">Spring
        Modules project</ulink>.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="new-in-2-migrating-ibatis">
        <title>iBATIS</title>

        <para>Please note that support for iBATIS SQL Maps 1.3 has been removed.
        If you haven't done so already, upgrade to iBATIS SQL Maps 2.3.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="new-in-2-migrating-hibernate">
        <title>Hibernate</title>

        <para>As of Spring 2.5, support for Hibernate 2.1 and Hibernate 3.0
        has been removed. If you haven't done so already, upgrade to
        Hibernate 3.1 or higher.</para>

        <para>If you need to stick with Hibernate 2.1 or 3.0 for the time
        being, we recommend to keep using the Spring Framework version
        2.0.7/2.0.8 which still supports those versions of Hibernate.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="new-in-2-migrating-jdo">
        <title>JDO</title>

        <para>As of Spring 2.5, support for JDO 1.0 has been removed.
        If you haven't done so already, upgrade to JDO 2.0 or higher.</para>

        <para>If you need to stick with JDO 1.0 for the time being,
        we recommend to keep using the Spring Framework version
        2.0.7/2.0.8 which still supports that version of JDO.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="new-in-2-migrating-UrlFilenameViewController">
        <title><classname>UrlFilenameViewController</classname></title>

        <para>Since Spring 2.0, the view name that is determined by the
        <classname>UrlFilenameViewController</classname> now takes into
        account the nested path of the request. This is a breaking change
        from the original contract of the
        <classname>UrlFilenameViewController</classname>, and means that if
        you are upgrading from Spring 1.x to Spring 2.x and you are using this
        class you <emphasis>might</emphasis> have to change your Spring Web
        MVC configuration slightly. Refer to the class level Javadocs of the
        <classname>UrlFilenameViewController</classname> to see examples of
        the new contract for view name determination.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="new-in-2-other-applications">
    <title>Updated sample applications</title>

    <para>A number of the sample applications have also been updated to
    showcase the new and improved features of Spring 2.0. So do take the time
    to investigate them. The aforementioned sample applications can be found
    in the <filename class="directory">'samples'</filename> directory of the
    full Spring distribution
    (<filename>'spring-with-dependencies.[zip|tar.gz]'</filename>).</para>

    <para>Spring 2.5 features revised versions of the PetClinic and PetPortal sample
    applications, reengineered from the ground up for leveraging Spring 2.5's
    annotation configuration features. It also uses Java 5 autoboxing, generics,
    varargs and the enhanced for loop. A Java 5 or 6 SDK is now required to build and
    run the sample. Check out PetClinic and PetPortal to get an impression of what
    Spring 2.5 has to offer!</para>
  </section>

  <section id="new-in-2-other-documentation">
    <title>Improved documentation</title>

    <para>The Spring reference documentation has also substantially been
    updated to reflect all of the above features new in Spring 2.0 and 2.5. 
    While every effort has been made to ensure that there are no errors in this
    documentation, some errors may nevertheless have crept in. If you do spot
    any typos or even more serious errors, and you can spare a few cycles
    during lunch, please do bring the error to the attention of the Spring
    team by <ulink
    url="http://opensource.atlassian.com/projects/spring/">raising an
    issue</ulink>.</para>

    <para>Special thanks to Arthur Loder for his tireless proofreading of the
    Spring Framework reference documentation and JavaDocs.</para>
  </section>

</chapter>
