<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="rest">
  <title>REST support</title>

  <section id="rest-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The goal of Spring's REST support is to make the development of
    RESTful Web services and applications easier.</para>

    <para>Client-side access to RESTful resources is greatly simplified using
    Spring <classname>RestTemplate</classname>.
    <classname>RestTemplate</classname> follows in the footsteps of other
    template classes in Spring such as <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> and
    <classname>JmsTemplate</classname>. Instead of dealing with a verbose
    lower level API such as Apache Commons <classname>HttpClient</classname>
    to create RESTful request, RestTemplate provides one liner methods that
    are purpose built for RESTful programming.</para>

    <para>On the server-side, Spring's REST support is based upon Spring's
    existing annotation based MVC framework. (For those interested in the
    rational for that decision, and for not implementing JAX-RS, read Arjen
    Poutsma's SpringSource TeamBlog <ulink
    url="http://blog.springsource.com/2009/03/08/rest-in-spring-3-mvc/">entry</ulink>.)
    With little effort, you can marshall data out of a RESTful request using
    <classname>@RequestMapping</classname> and
    <classname>@PathVariable</classname> annotations and return different
    views as determined by the request's <literal>Context-Type</literal>
    header.</para>

    <para>In this chapter we describe all the features of Spring's REST
    support. It is divided into two main chapters, one for the server-side and
    one for the client-side. For those new to Spring's <link linkend="mvc">MVC
    framework</link>, you may want to read through the reference documentation
    on <link linkend="mvc-annotation">annotation-based controller
    configuration</link> to understand the general programming model.</para>
  </section>


    <section id="rest-views">
      <title>Views</title>

      <para>Several views were added in Spring 3 to help support creating
      RESTful services. They are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><classname>AbstractAtomFeedView</classname> - returns an Atom
          feed</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><classname>AbstractRssFeedView</classname> - returns a RSS
          feed</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><classname>MarshallingView</classname> - returns an XML
          representation using Spring's Object to XML mapping (OXM)
          functionality</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <note>
        <para>Available separately is the
        <classname>JacksonJsonView</classname> included as part of the Spring
        JavaScript project.</para>
      </note>

      <section id="rest-feedview">
        <title>Feed Views</title>

        <para>Both <classname>AbstractAtomFeedView</classname> and
        <classname>AbstractRssFeedView</classname> inherit from the base class
        <classname>AbstractFeedView</classname> and are used to provide Atom
        and RSS Feed views respectfully. They are based on java.net's <ulink
        url="https://rome.dev.java.net">ROME</ulink> project and are located
        in the package
        <literal>org.springframework.web.servlet.view.feed</literal>.</para>

        <para><classname>AbstractAtomFeedView</classname> requires you to
        implement the <methodname>buildFeedEntries</methodname> method and
        optionally override the <methodname>buildFeedMetadata</methodname>
        method (the default implementation is empty), as shown below</para>

        <programlisting language="java">public class SampleContentAtomView extends AbstractAtomFeedView {

  @Override
  protected void buildFeedMetadata(Map&lt;String, Object&gt; model, Feed feed, 
                                   HttpServletRequest request) {
    // implementation omitted
  }

  @Override
  protected List&lt;Entry&gt; buildFeedEntries(Map&lt;String, Object&gt; model,
                                         HttpServletRequest request, 
                                         HttpServletResponse response) throws Exception {

   // implementation omitted
  }
}</programlisting>

        <para>Similar requirements apply for implementing
        <classname>AbstractRssFeedView</classname>, as shown below</para>

        <programlisting language="java">public class SampleContentAtomView extends AbstractRssFeedView {

  @Override   
  protected void buildFeedMetadata(Map&lt;String, Object&gt; model, Channel feed, 
                                   HttpServletRequest request) {
    // implementation omitted
  }

  @Override
  protected List&lt;Item&gt; buildFeedItems(Map&lt;String, Object&gt; model,
                                      HttpServletRequest request, 
                                      HttpServletResponse response) throws Exception {
    // implementation omitted
  }

}</programlisting>

        <para>The <methodname>buildFeedItems</methodname> and
        <methodname>buildFeedEntires</methodname> pass in the HTTP request in
        case you need to access the Locale. The HTTP response is passed in
        only for the setting of cookies or other HTTP headers. The feed will
        automatically be written to the response object after the method
        returns.</para>

        <para>For an example of creating a Atom view please refer to Alef
        Arendsen's SpringSource TeamBlog <ulink
        url="http://blog.springsource.com/2009/03/16/adding-an-atom-view-to-an-application-using-springs-rest-support/">entry</ulink>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>XML Marshalling View</title>

        <para>The <classname>MarhsallingView</classname> uses a XML
        <interfacename>Marshaller</interfacename> defined in the
        <classname>org.springframework.oxm</classname> package to render the
        response content as XML. The object to be marshalled can be set
        explicitly using <classname>MarhsallingView</classname>'s
        <property>modelKey</property> bean property. Alternatively, the view
        will iterate over all model properties marhsall only those types that
        are supported by the <interfacename>Marshaller</interfacename>. For
        more information on the functionality in the
        <classname>org.springframework.oxm</classname> package refer to the
        chapter <link linkend="oxm">Marshalling XML using O/X
        Mappers</link>.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="rest-method-conversion">
      <title>HTTP Method Conversion</title>

      <para>A key principle of REST is the use of the Uniform Interface. This
      means that all resources (URLs) can be manipulated using the same four
      HTTP methods: GET, PUT, POST, and DELETE. For each methods, the HTTP
      specification defines the exact semantics. For instance, a GET should
      always be a safe operation, meaning that is has no side effects, and a
      PUT or DELETE should be idempotent, meaning that you can repeat these
      operations over and over again, but the end result should be the same.
      While HTTP defines these four methods, HTML only supports two: GET and
      POST. Fortunately, there are two possible workarounds: you can either
      use JavaScript to do your PUT or DELETE, or simply do a POST with the
      'real' method as an additional parameter (modeled as a hidden input
      field in an HTML form). This latter trick is what Spring's
      <classname>HiddenHttpMethodFilter</classname> does. This filter is a
      plain Servlet Filter and therefore it can be used in combination with
      any web framework (not just Spring MVC). Simply add this filter to your
      web.xml, and a POST with a hidden _method parameter will be converted
      into the corresponding HTTP method request.</para>

      <section id="rest-form-tags">
        <title>Supporting Spring form tags</title>

        <para>To support HTTP method conversion the Spring MVC form tag was
        updated to support setting the HTTP method. For example, the following
        snippet taken from the updated Petclinic sample</para>

        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;form:form method="delete"&gt;
    &lt;p class="submit"&gt;&lt;input type="submit" value="Delete Pet"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/form:form&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>This will actually perform an HTTP POST, with the 'real' DELETE
        method hidden behind a request parameter, to be picked up by the
        <classname>HiddenHttpMethodFilter</classname>. The corresponding
        @Controller method is shown below</para>

        <programlisting language="java">@RequestMapping(method = RequestMethod.DELETE)
public String deletePet(@PathVariable int ownerId, @PathVariable int petId) {
    this.clinic.deletePet(petId);
    return "redirect:/owners/" + ownerId;
}</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="rest-etag">
      <title>ETag support</title>

      <para>An <ulink
      url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTTP_ETag">ETag</ulink> (entity tag)
      is an HTTP response header returned by an HTTP/1.1 compliant web server
      used to determine change in content at a given URL. It can be considered
      to be the more sophisticated successor to the
      <literal>Last-Modified</literal> header. When a server returns a
      representation with an ETag header, the client can use this header in
      subsequent GETs, in an <literal>If-None-Match</literal> header. If the
      content has not changed, the server will return <literal>304: Not
      Modified</literal>.</para>

      <para>Support for ETags is provided by the servlet filter
      <classname>ShallowEtagHeaderFilter</classname>. Since it is a plain
      Servlet Filter, and thus can be used in combination with any web
      framework. The <classname>ShallowEtagHeaderFilter</classname> filter
      creates so-called shallow ETags (as opposed to deep ETags, more about
      that later). The way it works is quite simple: the filter simply caches
      the content of the rendered JSP (or other content), generates an MD5
      hash over that, and returns that as an ETag header in the response. The
      next time a client sends a request for the same resource, it uses that
      hash as the <literal>If-None-Match</literal> value. The filter notices
      this, renders the view again, and compares the two hashes. If they are
      equal, a <literal>304</literal> is returned. It is important to note
      that this filter will not save processing power, as the view is still
      rendered. The only thing it saves is bandwidth, as the rendered response
      is not sent back over the wire.</para>

      <para>Deep ETags are a bit more complicated. In this case, the ETag is
      based on the underlying domain objects, RDMBS tables, etc. Using this
      approach, no content is generated unless the underlying data has
      changed. Unfortunately, implementing this approach in a generic way is
      much more difficult than shallow ETags. Spring may provide support for
      deep ETags in a later release by relying on JPA's @Version annotation,
      or an AspectJ aspect.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="rest-exception">
      <title>Exception Handling</title>

      <para>The <classname>@ExceptionHandler</classname> method annotation is
      used within a controller to specify which method will be invoked when an
      exception of a specific type is thrown during the execution of
      controller methods. For example</para>

      <programlisting language="java">@Controller
public class SimpleController {

 // other controller method omitted

 @ExceptionHandler(IOException.class)
 public String handleIOException(IOException ex, HttpServletRequest request) {
  return ClassUtils.getShortName(ex.getClass());
 }
}</programlisting>

      <para>will invoke the 'handlerIOException' method when a
      <classname>java.io.IOException</classname> is thrown.</para>

      <para>The <classname>@ExceptionHandler</classname> value can be set to
      an array of Exception types. If an exception is thrown matches one of
      the types in the list, then the method annotated with the matching
      <classname>@ExceptionHandler</classname> will be invoked. If the
      annotation value is not set then the exception types listed as method
      arguments are used.</para>

      <para>Much like standard controller methods annotated with a
      <classname>@RequestMapping</classname> annotation, the method arguments
      and return values of <classname>@ExceptionHandler</classname> methods
      are very flexible. For example, the
      <classname>HttpServletRequest</classname> can be accessed in Servlet
      environments and the <classname>PortletRequest</classname> in Portlet
      environments. The return type can be a <classname>String</classname>,
      which is interpreted as a view name or a
      <classname>ModelAndView</classname> object. Please refer to the API
      documentation for more details.</para>
    </section>

</chapter>
