<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="beans-factory-scopes"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="
        http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
        http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd">
  <title>Bean scopes</title>

  <para>When you create a bean definition, you create a
    <emphasis>recipe</emphasis> for creating actual instances of the class
    defined by that bean definition. The idea that a bean definition is a recipe
    is important, because it means that, as with a class, you can create many
    object instances from a single recipe.</para>

  <para>You can control not only the various dependencies and configuration
    values that are to be plugged into an object that is created from a
    particular bean definition, but also the <firstterm>scope</firstterm> of the
    objects created from a particular bean definition. This approach is powerful
    and flexible in that you can <emphasis>choose</emphasis> the scope of the
    objects you create through configuration instead of having to bake in the
    scope of an object at the Java class level. Beans can be defined to be
    deployed in one of a number of scopes: out of the box, the Spring Framework
    supports five scopes, three of which are available only if you use a
    web-aware <interfacename>ApplicationContext</interfacename>.</para>

  <para>The following scopes are supported out of the box. You can also create
    <link linkend="beans-factory-scopes-custom">a custom scope.</link></para>

  <table xml:id="beans-factory-scopes-tbl">
    <title>Bean scopes</title>

    <tgroup cols="2">
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry align="center">Scope</entry>

          <entry align="center">Description</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>

      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry><para> <link linkend="beans-factory-scopes-singleton"
            >singleton</link> </para></entry>

          <entry><para>(Default) Scopes a single bean definition to a single
            object instance per Spring IoC container.</para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para> <link linkend="beans-factory-scopes-prototype"
            >prototype</link> </para></entry>

          <entry><para>Scopes a single bean definition to any number of object
            instances.</para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para> <link linkend="beans-factory-scopes-request"
            >request</link> </para></entry>

          <entry><para>Scopes a single bean definition to the lifecycle of a
            single HTTP request; that is, each HTTP request has its own instance
            of a bean created off the back of a single bean definition. Only
            valid in the context of a web-aware Spring
            <interfacename>ApplicationContext</interfacename>.</para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para> <link linkend="beans-factory-scopes-session"
            >session</link> </para></entry>

          <entry><para>Scopes a single bean definition to the lifecycle of an
            HTTP <interfacename>Session</interfacename>. Only valid in the
            context of a web-aware Spring
            <interfacename>ApplicationContext</interfacename>.</para></entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><para> <link linkend="beans-factory-scopes-global-session"
            >global session</link> </para></entry>

          <entry><para>Scopes a single bean definition to the lifecycle of a
            global HTTP <interfacename>Session</interfacename>. Typically only
            valid when used in a portlet context. Only valid in the context of a
            web-aware Spring
            <interfacename>ApplicationContext</interfacename>.</para></entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>

  <note>
    <title>Thread-scoped beans</title>

    <para>As of Spring 3.0, a <emphasis>thread scope</emphasis> is available,
      but is not registered by default. For more information, see the
      documentation for <link
      xl:href="http://static.springsource.org/spring/docs/current/api/org/springframework/context/support/SimpleThreadScope.html"
      >SimpleThreadScope</link>. For instructions on how to register this or
      any other custom scope, see <xref
      linkend="beans-factory-scopes-custom-using"/>.</para>
  </note>

  <section xml:id="beans-factory-scopes-singleton">
    <title>The singleton scope</title>

    <para>Only one <emphasis>shared</emphasis> instance of a singleton bean is
      managed, and all requests for beans with an id or ids matching that bean
      definition result in that one specific bean instance being returned by the
      Spring container.</para>

    <para>To put it another way, when you define a bean definition and it is
      scoped as a singleton, the Spring IoC container creates <emphasis>exactly
      one</emphasis> instance of the object defined by that bean definition.
      This single instance is stored in a cache of such singleton beans, and
      <emphasis>all subsequent requests and references</emphasis> for that named
      bean return the cached object.</para>

    <para><mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/singleton.png" format="PNG"
            width="400"/>
      </imageobject>

      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/singleton.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>Spring's concept of a singleton bean differs from the Singleton
      pattern as defined in the Gang of Four (GoF) patterns book. The GoF
      Singleton hard-codes the scope of an object such that one <emphasis>and
      only one</emphasis> instance of a particular class is created<emphasis>
      per <classname>ClassLoader</classname></emphasis>. The scope of the Spring
      singleton is best described as <emphasis>per container and per
      bean</emphasis>. This means that if you define one bean for a particular
      class in a single Spring container, then the Spring container creates one
      <emphasis>and only one</emphasis> instance of the class defined by that
      bean definition. <emphasis>The singleton scope is the default scope in
      Spring</emphasis>. To define a bean as a singleton in XML, you would
      write, for example:</para>

    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;bean id="accountService" class="com.foo.DefaultAccountService"/&gt;

<lineannotation>&lt;!-- the following is equivalent, though redundant (singleton scope is the default) --&gt;</lineannotation>
&lt;bean id="accountService" class="com.foo.DefaultAccountService" scope="singleton"/&gt;</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="beans-factory-scopes-prototype">
    <title>The prototype scope</title>

    <para>The non-singleton, prototype scope of bean deployment results in the
      <emphasis>creation of a new bean instance</emphasis> every time a request
      for that specific bean is made. That is, the bean is injected into another
      bean or you request it through a <literal>getBean()</literal> method call
      on the container. As a rule, use the prototype scope for all stateful
      beans and the singleton scope for stateless beans.</para>

    <para>The following diagram illustrates the Spring prototype scope.
      <emphasis>A data access object (DAO) is not typically configured as a
      prototype, because a typical DAO does not hold any conversational state;
      it was just easier for this author to reuse the core of the singleton
      diagram.</emphasis><!--First it says diagram illustrates scope, but then says it's not typical of a prototype scope. Why not use realistic one? --></para>

    <para><mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/prototype.png" format="PNG"
            width="400" />
      </imageobject>

      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/prototype.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>

    <para>The following example defines a bean as a prototype in XML:</para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><lineannotation>&lt;!-- using spring-beans-2.0.dtd --&gt;</lineannotation>
&lt;bean id="accountService" class="com.foo.DefaultAccountService" scope="prototype"/&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>In contrast to the other scopes, Spring does not manage the complete
      lifecycle of a prototype bean: the container instantiates, configures, and
      otherwise assembles a prototype object, and hands it to the client, with
      no further record of that prototype instance. Thus, although
      <emphasis>initialization</emphasis> lifecycle callback methods are called
      on all objects regardless of scope, in the case of prototypes, configured
      <emphasis>destruction</emphasis> lifecycle callbacks are
      <emphasis>not</emphasis> called. The client code must clean up
      prototype-scoped objects and release expensive resources that the
      prototype bean(s) are holding. To get the Spring container to release
      resources held by prototype-scoped beans, try using a custom <link
      linkend="beans-factory-extension-bpp">bean post-processor</link>, which
      holds a reference to beans that need to be cleaned up.</para>

    <para>In some respects, the Spring container's role in regard to a
      prototype-scoped bean is a replacement for the Java <literal>new</literal>
      operator. All lifecycle management past that point must be handled by the
      client. (For details on the lifecycle of a bean in the Spring container,
      see <xref linkend="beans-factory-lifecycle"/>.)</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="beans-factory-scopes-sing-prot-interaction">
    <title>Singleton beans with prototype-bean dependencies</title>

    <para>When you use singleton-scoped beans with dependencies on prototype
      beans, be aware that <emphasis>dependencies are resolved at instantiation
      time</emphasis>. Thus if you dependency-inject a prototype-scoped bean
      into a singleton-scoped bean, a new prototype bean is instantiated and
      then dependency-injected into the singleton bean. The prototype instance
      is the sole instance that is ever supplied to the singleton-scoped
      bean.</para>

    <para>However, suppose you want the singleton-scoped bean to acquire a new
      instance of the prototype-scoped bean repeatedly at runtime. You cannot
      dependency-inject a prototype-scoped bean into your singleton bean,
      because that injection occurs only <emphasis>once</emphasis>, when the
      Spring container is instantiating the singleton bean and resolving and
      injecting its dependencies. If you need a new instance of a prototype bean
      at runtime more than once, see <xref
      linkend="beans-factory-method-injection"/></para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="beans-factory-scopes-other">
    <title>Request, session, and global session scopes</title>

    <para>The <literal>request</literal>, <literal>session</literal>, and
      <literal>global session</literal> scopes are <emphasis>only</emphasis>
      available if you use a web-aware Spring
      <interfacename>ApplicationContext</interfacename> implementation (such as
      <classname>XmlWebApplicationContext</classname>). If you use these scopes
      with regular Spring IoC containers such as the
      <classname>ClassPathXmlApplicationContext</classname>, you get an
      <classname>IllegalStateException</classname> complaining about an unknown
      bean scope.</para>

    <section xml:id="beans-factory-scopes-other-web-configuration">
      <title>Initial web configuration</title>

      <para>To support the scoping of beans at the <literal>request</literal>,
        <literal>session</literal>, and <literal>global session</literal> levels
        (web-scoped beans), some minor initial configuration is required before
        you define your beans. (This initial setup is <emphasis>not</emphasis>
        required for the standard scopes, singleton and prototype.)</para>

      <para>How you accomplish this initial setup depends on your particular
        Servlet environment..</para>

      <para>If you access scoped beans within Spring Web MVC, in effect, within
        a request that is processed by the Spring
        <classname>DispatcherServlet</classname>, or
        <classname>DispatcherPortlet</classname>, then no special setup is
        necessary: <classname>DispatcherServlet</classname> and
        <classname>DispatcherPortlet</classname> already expose all relevant
        state.</para>

      <para>If you use a Servlet 2.4+ web container, with requests processed
        outside of Spring's DispatcherServlet (for example, when using JSF or
        Struts), you need to add the following
        <interfacename>javax.servlet.ServletRequestListener</interfacename> to
        the declarations in your web applications <literal>web.xml</literal>
        file:</para>

      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;web-app&gt;
...
&lt;listener&gt;
  &lt;listener-class&gt;
      org.springframework.web.context.request.RequestContextListener
  &lt;/listener-class&gt;
&lt;/listener&gt;
...
&lt;/web-app&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>If you use an older web container (Servlet 2.3), use the provided
        <interfacename>javax.servlet.Filter</interfacename> implementation. The
        following snippet of XML configuration must be included in the
        <literal>web.xml</literal> file of your web application if you want to
        access web-scoped beans in requests outside of Spring's
        DispatcherServlet on a Servlet 2.3 container. (The filter mapping
        depends on the surrounding web application configuration, so you must
        change it as appropriate.)</para>

      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;web-app&gt;
..
&lt;filter&gt;
  &lt;filter-name&gt;requestContextFilter&lt;/filter-name&gt;
  &lt;filter-class&gt;org.springframework.web.filter.RequestContextFilter&lt;/filter-class&gt;
&lt;/filter&gt;
&lt;filter-mapping&gt;
  &lt;filter-name&gt;requestContextFilter&lt;/filter-name&gt;
  &lt;url-pattern&gt;/*&lt;/url-pattern&gt;
&lt;/filter-mapping&gt;
...
&lt;/web-app&gt;</programlisting>

      <para><classname>DispatcherServlet</classname>,
        <classname>RequestContextListener</classname> and
        <classname>RequestContextFilter</classname> all do exactly the same
        thing, namely bind the HTTP request object to the
        <classname>Thread</classname> that is servicing that request. This makes
        beans that are request- and session-scoped available further down the
        call chain.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="beans-factory-scopes-request">
      <title>Request scope</title>

      <para>Consider the following bean definition:</para>

      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;bean id="loginAction" class="com.foo.LoginAction" scope="request"/&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>The Spring container creates a new instance of the
        <classname>LoginAction</classname> bean by using the
        <literal>loginAction</literal> bean definition for each and every HTTP
        request. That is, the <literal>loginAction</literal> bean is scoped at
        the HTTP request level. You can change the internal state of the
        instance that is created as much as you want, because other instances
        created from the same <literal>loginAction</literal> bean definition
        will not see these changes in state; they are particular to an
        individual request. When the request completes processing, the bean that
        is scoped to the request is discarded.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="beans-factory-scopes-session">
      <title>Session scope</title>

      <para>Consider the following bean definition:</para>

      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;bean id="userPreferences" class="com.foo.UserPreferences" scope="session"/&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>The Spring container creates a new instance of the
        <classname>UserPreferences</classname> bean by using the
        <literal>userPreferences</literal> bean definition for the lifetime of a
        single HTTP <interfacename>Session</interfacename>. In other words, the
        <literal>userPreferences</literal> bean is effectively scoped at the
        HTTP <interfacename>Session</interfacename> level. As with
        <literal>request-scoped</literal> beans, you can change the internal
        state of the instance that is created as much as you want, knowing that
        other HTTP <interfacename>Session</interfacename> instances that are
        also using instances created from the same
        <literal>userPreferences</literal> bean definition do not see these
        changes in state, because they are particular to an individual HTTP
        <interfacename>Session</interfacename>. When the HTTP
        <interfacename>Session</interfacename> is eventually discarded, the bean
        that is scoped to that particular HTTP
        <interfacename>Session</interfacename> is also discarded.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="beans-factory-scopes-global-session">
      <title>Global session scope</title>

      <para>Consider the following bean definition:</para>

      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;bean id="userPreferences" class="com.foo.UserPreferences" scope="globalSession"/&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>The <literal>global session</literal> scope is similar to the
        standard HTTP <interfacename>Session</interfacename> scope (<link
        linkend="beans-factory-scopes-session">described above</link>), and
        applies only in the context of portlet-based web applications. The
        portlet specification defines the notion of a global
        <interfacename>Session</interfacename> that is shared among all portlets
        that make up a single portlet web application. Beans defined at the
        <literal>global session</literal> scope are scoped (or bound) to the
        lifetime of the global portlet
        <interfacename>Session</interfacename>.</para>

      <para>If you write a standard Servlet-based web application and you define
        one or more beans as having <literal>global session</literal> scope, the
        standard HTTP <interfacename>Session</interfacename> scope is used, and
        no error is raised.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="beans-factory-scopes-other-injection">
      <title>Scoped beans as dependencies</title>

      <para>The Spring IoC container manages not only the instantiation of your
        objects (beans), but also the wiring up of collaborators (or
        dependencies). If you want to inject (for example) an HTTP request
        scoped bean into another bean, you must inject an AOP proxy in place of
        the scoped bean. That is, you need to inject a proxy object that exposes
        the same public interface as the scoped object but that can also
        retrieve the real, target object from the relevant scope (for example,
        an HTTP request) and delegate method calls onto the real object.</para>

      <note>
        <para>You <emphasis>do not</emphasis> need to use the
          <literal>&lt;aop:scoped-proxy/&gt;</literal> in conjunction with beans
          that are scoped as <literal>singletons</literal> or
          <literal>prototypes</literal>.</para>
      </note>

      <para>The configuration in the following example is only one line, but it
        is important to understand the <quote>why</quote> as well as the
        <quote>how</quote> behind it.</para>

      <!--What is this example supposed to show?-->

      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;beans xmlns="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns:aop="http://www.springframework.org/schema/aop"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans
         http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans-3.0.xsd
         http://www.springframework.org/schema/aop
         http://www.springframework.org/schema/aop/spring-aop-3.0.xsd"&gt;

  <lineannotation>&lt;!-- an HTTP Session-scoped bean exposed as a proxy --&gt;</lineannotation>
  &lt;bean id="userPreferences" class="com.foo.UserPreferences" scope="session"&gt;

        <lineannotation>&lt;!-- instructs the container to proxy the surrounding bean --&gt;</lineannotation>
        &lt;aop:scoped-proxy/&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;

  <lineannotation>&lt;!-- a singleton-scoped bean injected with a proxy to the above bean --&gt;</lineannotation>
  &lt;bean id="userService" class="com.foo.SimpleUserService"&gt;

      <lineannotation>&lt;!-- a reference to the proxied userPreferences bean --&gt;</lineannotation>
      &lt;property name="userPreferences" ref="userPreferences"/&gt;

  &lt;/bean&gt;
&lt;/beans&gt;
</programlisting>

      <para>To create such a proxy, you insert a child
        <literal>&lt;aop:scoped-proxy/&gt;</literal> element into a scoped bean
        definition.  See <xref
        linkend="beans-factory-scopes-other-injection-proxies"/> and <xref
        linkend="xsd-config"/>.) Why do definitions of beans scoped at the
        <literal>request</literal>, <literal>session</literal>,
        <literal>globalSession</literal> and custom-scope levels require the
        <literal>&lt;aop:scoped-proxy/&gt;</literal> element ? Let's examine the
        following singleton bean definition and contrast it with what you need
        to define for the aforementioned scopes. (The following
        <literal>userPreferences</literal> bean definition as it stands is
        <emphasis>incomplete.)</emphasis></para>

      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;bean id="userPreferences" class="com.foo.UserPreferences" scope="session"/&gt;

&lt;bean id="userManager" class="com.foo.UserManager"&gt;
  &lt;property name="userPreferences" ref="userPreferences"/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>In the preceding example, the singleton bean
        <literal>userManager</literal> is injected with a reference to the HTTP
        <interfacename>Session</interfacename>-scoped bean
        <literal>userPreferences</literal>. The salient point here is that the
        <literal>userManager</literal> bean is a singleton: it will be
        instantiated <emphasis>exactly once</emphasis> per container, and its
        dependencies (in this case only one, the
        <literal>userPreferences</literal> bean) are also injected only once.
        This means that the <literal>userManager</literal> bean will only
        operate on the exact same <literal>userPreferences</literal> object,
        that is, the one that it was originally injected with.</para>

      <!-- MLP: Beverly to review paragraph -->

      <para>This is <emphasis>not</emphasis> the behavior you want when
        injecting a shorter-lived scoped bean into a longer-lived scoped bean,
        for example injecting an HTTP
        <interfacename>Session</interfacename>-scoped collaborating bean as a
        dependency into singleton bean. Rather, you need a single
        <literal>userManager</literal> object, and for the lifetime of an HTTP
        <interfacename>Session</interfacename>, you need a
        <literal>userPreferences</literal> object that is specific to said HTTP
        <interfacename>Session</interfacename>. Thus the container creates an
        object that exposes the exact same public interface as the
        <classname>UserPreferences</classname> class (ideally an object that
        <emphasis>is a</emphasis> <classname>UserPreferences</classname>
        instance) which can fetch the real
        <classname>UserPreferences</classname> object from the scoping mechanism
        (HTTP request, <interfacename>Session</interfacename>, etc.). The
        container injects this proxy object into the
        <literal>userManager</literal> bean, which is unaware that this
        <classname>UserPreferences</classname> reference is a proxy. In this
        example, when a <interfacename>UserManager</interfacename> instance
        invokes a method on the dependency-injected
        <classname>UserPreferences</classname> object, it actually is invoking a
        method on the proxy. The proxy then fetches the real
        <classname>UserPreferences</classname> object from (in this case) the
        HTTP <interfacename>Session</interfacename>, and delegates the method
        invocation onto the retrieved real
        <classname>UserPreferences</classname> object.</para>

      <para>Thus you need the following, correct and complete, configuration
        when injecting <literal>request-</literal>, <literal>session-</literal>,
        and <literal>globalSession-scoped</literal> beans into collaborating
        objects:</para>

      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;bean id="userPreferences" class="com.foo.UserPreferences" scope="session"&gt;
  <literal>&lt;aop:scoped-proxy/&gt;</literal>
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="userManager" class="com.foo.UserManager"&gt;
  &lt;property name="userPreferences" ref="userPreferences"/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

      <section xml:id="beans-factory-scopes-other-injection-proxies">
        <title>Choosing the type of proxy to create</title>

        <para>By default, when the Spring container creates a proxy for a bean
          that is marked up with the
          <literal>&lt;aop:scoped-proxy/&gt;</literal> element, <emphasis>a
          CGLIB-based class proxy is created</emphasis>.</para>

        <para><emphasis>Note: CGLIB proxies only intercept public method
          calls!</emphasis> Do not call non-public methods on such a proxy; they
          will not be delegated to the scoped target object.</para>

        <para>Alternatively, you can configure the Spring container to create
          standard JDK interface-based proxies for such scoped beans, by
          specifying <literal>false</literal> for the value of the
          <literal>proxy-target-class</literal> attribute of the
          <literal>&lt;aop:scoped-proxy/&gt;</literal> element. Using JDK
          interface-based proxies means that you do not need additional
          libraries in your application classpath to effect such proxying.
          However, it also means that the class of the scoped bean must
          implement at least one interface, and <emphasis>that all</emphasis>
          collaborators into which the scoped bean is injected must reference
          the bean through one of its interfaces.</para>

        <programlisting language="xml"><lineannotation>&lt;!-- DefaultUserPreferences implements the UserPreferences interface --&gt;</lineannotation>
&lt;bean id="userPreferences" class="com.foo.DefaultUserPreferences" scope="session"&gt;
  &lt;aop:scoped-proxy proxy-target-class="false"<literal/>/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="userManager" class="com.foo.UserManager"&gt;
  &lt;property name="userPreferences" ref="userPreferences"/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>For more detailed information about choosing class-based or
          interface-based proxying, see <xref linkend="aop-proxying"/>.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="beans-factory-scopes-custom">
    <title>Custom scopes</title>

    <para>As of Spring 2.0, the bean scoping mechanism is extensible. You can
      define your own scopes, or even redefine existing scopes, although the
      latter is considered bad practice and you <emphasis>cannot</emphasis>
      override the built-in <literal>singleton</literal> and
      <literal>prototype</literal> scopes.</para>

    <section xml:id="beans-factory-scopes-custom-creating">
      <title>Creating a custom scope</title>

      <para>To integrate your custom scope(s) into the Spring container, you
        need to implement the
        <interfacename>org.springframework.beans.factory.config.Scope</interfacename>
        interface, which is described in this section. For an idea of how to
        implement your own scopes, see the <interfacename>Scope</interfacename>
        implementations that are supplied with the Spring Framework itself and
        the <link
        xl:href="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/current/api/org/springframework/beans/factory/config/Scope.html"
        >Scope Javadoc</link>, which explains the methods you need to implement
        in more detail.</para>

      <para>The <literal>Scope</literal> interface has four methods to get
        objects from the scope, remove them from the scope, and allow them to be
        destroyed.</para>

      <para>The following method returns the object from the underlying scope.
        The session scope implementation, for example, returns the
        session-scoped bean (and if it does not exist, the method returns a new
        instance of the bean, after having bound it to the session for future
        reference).<!--How can it return a a new instance of a bean that doesn't exist? Revise to clarify.--></para>

      <programlisting language="java">Object get(String name, ObjectFactory objectFactory)</programlisting>

      <para>The following method removes the object from the underlying scope.
        The session scope implementation for example, removes the session-scoped
        bean from the underlying session. The object should be returned, but you
        can return null if the object with the specified name is not
        found.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">Object remove(String name)</programlisting>

      <para>The following method registers the callbacks the scope should
        execute when it is destroyed or when the specified object in the scope
        is destroyed. Refer to the Javadoc or a Spring scope implementation for
        more information on destruction callbacks.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">void registerDestructionCallback(String name, Runnable destructionCallback)</programlisting>

      <para>The following method obtains the conversation identifier for the
        underlying scope. This identifier is different for each scope. For a
        session scoped implementation, this identifier can be the session
        identifier.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">String getConversationId()</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="beans-factory-scopes-custom-using">
      <title>Using a custom scope</title>

      <para>After you write and test one or more custom
        <interfacename>Scope</interfacename> implementations, you need to make
        the Spring container aware of your new scope(s). The following method is
        the central method to register a new
        <interfacename>Scope</interfacename> with the Spring container:</para>

      <programlisting language="java">void registerScope(String scopeName, Scope scope);</programlisting>

      <para>This method is declared on the
        <interfacename>ConfigurableBeanFactory</interfacename> interface, which
        is available on most of the concrete
        <interfacename>ApplicationContext</interfacename> implementations that
        ship with Spring via the BeanFactory property.</para>

      <para>The first argument to the <methodname>registerScope(..)</methodname>
        method is the unique name associated with a scope; examples of such
        names in the Spring container itself are <literal>singleton</literal>
        and <literal>prototype</literal>. The second argument to the
        <methodname>registerScope(..)</methodname> method is an actual instance
        of the custom <interfacename>Scope</interfacename> implementation that
        you wish to register and use.</para>

      <para>Suppose that you write your custom
        <interfacename>Scope</interfacename> implementation, and then register
        it as below.</para>

      <note>
        <para>The example below uses <literal>SimpleThreadScope</literal> which
          is included with Spring, but not registered by default. The
          instructions would be the same for your own custom
          <literal>Scope</literal> implementations.</para>
      </note>

      <programlisting language="java">
Scope threadScope = new SimpleThreadScope();
beanFactory.registerScope("thread", threadScope);</programlisting>

      <para>You then create bean definitions that adhere to the scoping rules of
        your custom <interfacename>Scope</interfacename>:</para>

      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;bean id="..." class="..." scope="thread"&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>With a custom <interfacename>Scope</interfacename> implementation,
        you are not limited to programmatic registration of the scope. You can
        also do the <interfacename>Scope</interfacename> registration
        declaratively, using the <classname>CustomScopeConfigurer</classname>
        class:</para>

      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;beans xmlns="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xmlns:aop="http://www.springframework.org/schema/aop"
     xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans
         http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans-3.0.xsd
         http://www.springframework.org/schema/aop
         http://www.springframework.org/schema/aop/spring-aop-3.0.xsd"&gt;

  &lt;bean class="org.springframework.beans.factory.config.CustomScopeConfigurer"&gt;
      &lt;property name="scopes"&gt;
          &lt;map&gt;
              &lt;entry key="thread"&gt;
                  &lt;bean class="org.springframework.context.support.SimpleThreadScope"/&gt;
              &lt;/entry&gt;
          &lt;/map&gt;
      &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;

  &lt;bean id="bar" class="x.y.Bar" scope="thread"&gt;
      &lt;property name="name" value="Rick"/&gt;
      &lt;aop:scoped-proxy/&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;

  &lt;bean id="foo" class="x.y.Foo"&gt;
      &lt;property name="bar" ref="bar"/&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;/beans&gt;</programlisting>

      <note>
        <para>When you place &lt;aop:scoped-proxy/&gt; in a
          <interfacename>FactoryBean</interfacename> implementation, it is the
          factory bean itself that is scoped, not the object returned from
          <methodname>getObject()</methodname>.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
